Guide to the George E. Osborne Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
George E. Osborne papers
1911-1977
SC0198
Osborne, George E. (George Edward), 1893-1977
8 Linear feet
These papers largely pertain to his teaching career at Stanford Law School and include correspondence, memoranda, curriculum materials, Law School publications and reports, and speeches. Other professional papers include correspondence with his publishers, 1938-61; and correspondence with legal scholars at Harvard, West Virginia, Minnesota, Stanford, Duke, Columbia, University of California, Chicago, and University of Colorado, 1920-51. Correspondents include Henry W. Ballantine, Herbert C. Jones, Marion R. Kirkwood, Douglas B. Maggs, Cyril C. Means, Justin Miller, Roscoe Pound, and William L. Prosser. Other items include a diary for 1930 and journals for 1956-1965; correspondence with George Crothers and information on Crothers Hall at Stanford; correspondence and typescript articles on the history of the Bohemian Grove; biographical materials; and photographs.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Scholar of mortgage and property law. Osborne received his LLB and JD degrees from Harvard in 1919 and 1920; before joining the faculty at the Stanford Law School in 1923, he taught at the Universities of West Virginia and Minnesota. He was appointed to the William Nelson Cromwell Professorship in 1953, which he held until his retirement in 1958. He died in 1977.
Description of the Collection
These papers largely pertain to his teaching career at Stanford Law School and include correspondence, memoranda, curriculum materials, Law School publications and reports, and speeches. Other professional papers include correspondence with his publishers, 1938-61; and correspondence with legal scholars at Harvard, West Virginia, Minnesota, Stanford, Duke, Columbia, University of California, Chicago, and University of Colorado, 1920-51. Correspondents include Henry W. Ballantine, Herbert C. Jones, Marion R. Kirkwood, Douglas B. Maggs, Cyril C. Means, Justin Miller, Roscoe Pound, and William L. Prosser. Other items include a diary for 1930 and journals for 1956-1965; correspondence with George Crothers and information on Crothers Hall at Stanford; correspondence and typescript articles on the history of the Bohemian Grove; biographical materials; and photographs.
Folders 19-29 contain correspondence; many are congratulatory on his retirement in 1958. The names noted for the alpha folders are not all-inclusive
Access Terms
Ballantine, Henry Winthrop, 1880-1951.; Bohemian Club (San Francisco, Calif.).; Crothers, George E. (George Edward), 1870-1957.; Jones, Herbert C. (Herbert Coffin), 1881-1970.; Kirkwood, Marion Rice, 1887-1978.; Maggs, Douglas Blount, 1899-1962; Means, Cyril C.; Miller, Justin.; Osborne, George E. (George Edward), 1893-1977; Pound, Roscoe.; Prosser, William Lloyd, 1898-; Stanford University. School of Law.; Law --Study and teaching.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Biographical (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Clippings re Osborne (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Clippings on labor negotiation (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Osborne, his remarks on his career (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Weigel, Stanley "About George Osborne," with letter, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Y. B. Newsletter [Stanford Law School], 1943-44 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Beardsley, Charles A., speech before Assoc. of American Law Schools, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - R-Plan speech and related papers (S.U. fundraising) 1942-45 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Ferguson, Kenneth, remarks at Law Dinner, April 18, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - S. U. assorted memos and committee papers (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Dean's Report to the Faculty of the Stanford Law School Jan. 1958 and 2 other reports (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Miscellany (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - S.U. Press releases and publications (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Photographs (1 labeled faculty picnic at Owens cabin, the 2nd is unlabeled – large group sitting at dinner), circa 1930 or 1931 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Stanford Law School assorted newsletters, etc. (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Athearn, Lucille, 1946-48 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Christopher, Warren, 1958, undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Slaff, George (2 letters were written while he was with the Red Cross during WWII in Africa and France and one is a carbon copy of his letter to Tresidder praising Osborne; the others are to Osborne), 1943-49 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - A-B (Charles Beardsley, George Brunn), 1947-58 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - C (Philip Conley, Aylett B. Cotton), 1925-58 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - D-E, 1948-72 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - F-G (Irving Fathchild, Robert J. Foley, Edwin L. Gerhardt), 1930-58 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - H (J. B. Haffner, Herbert L. Hahn, Harvey Hoshour), 1922-58 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - I-L, 1948-58 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - M (John Stewart Mitchell), 1931-58 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - O-R (Robert E. Paradise, Pete (Austin H.) Peck, Gilbert B. Perry, Harold O. Preston, Robert Ransom, James E. Reid), 1927-72 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - S-T, 1946-58 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - U-V (J. A. Wyckoff), 1930-58 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence with no last name or illegible (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Stanford Law School reports, publications, and correspondence, 1944-56 (Box 8)
  - California bar exam - correspondence, with various examples of the test, 1945 (Box 8)
  - Railroad labor cases - clippings and legal documents, 1951-54 (Box 8)
  - Crothers, George - correspondence, obituary, speeches (Box 8)
  - Crothers Hall Student Committee Report (Box 8)
  - Materials for discussion of Stanford trusts, 1946 (Box 8)
  - Crothers Hall - correspondence and plans, 1946 (Box 8)
  - Stanford legal history - correspondence and documents (Box 8)
  - Photograph (Box 8)
  - Roman Law course at S .U. - lectures and exams, 1931 (Box 9)
  - Personal Property course at S.U. - exams and notes, 1925-48 (Box 9)
  - S.U. class lists, class roll books, seating charts (Box 10)
  - S.U. class roll books (Box 11)
  - Readings in Roman Law by Roscoe Pound (mimeographed copy), 1927 (Box 12)
  - Annual Examinations in Law, Harvard University, 1915-1944 (Box 12)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-1998-198
  - To Do Lists/Notes, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - To Do Lists/ Notes, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - To Do Lists/ Notes, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - To Do Lists/ Notes, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - To Do Lists/ Notes, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - To Do Lists/ Notes, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Incoming (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Family (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Personal Papers: Clippings, Etc. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Personal Papers: Photographs (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Woolley, Edwin c., Handbook ofComposition. (1909) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Leather Billfold with business cards (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Memorial and Personal Effects (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Envelope to Louisa Howe: Memorial Information, Estate Documents, Letters, Photographs, Hastings Alumni Bulletin, Stanford Lawyer, Spring 1977 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Guest Book (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Portraits (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Stanford Lawyer (2 copies), Fall 1977 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Journal/Record Book, 1956 (Box 3)
  - Journal/Record Book, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Journal/Record Book, 1959 (Box 3)
  - Journal/Record Book, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Journal/Record Book, 1961 (Box 3)
  - Journal/Record Book, 1962 (Box 3)
  - Journal/Record Book, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Journal/Record Book, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Journal/Record Book, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Desk Set, Engraved (Box 4)
  - Loose Journal Items, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Loose Journal Items, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Loose Journal Items, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Loose Journal Items, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Loose Journal Items, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Loose Journal Items, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Loose Journal Items, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Loose Journal Items, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Loose Journal Items, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 9)